<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Paylogic Developers</title><link href="http://developer.paylogic.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://developer.paylogic.com/feeds/general.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://developer.paylogic.com/</id><updated>2013-06-19T18:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>You are welcome</title><link href="http://developer.paylogic.com/articles/you-are-welcome.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-19T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Berco Beute</name></author><id>tag:developer.paylogic.com,2013-06-19:articles/you-are-welcome.html</id><summary type="html">
&lt;div class="section" id="you-are-welcome"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id1"&gt;You are welcome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We at Paylogic are passionate about software. We have the craft of software engineering on a pedestal, we love to write clean code, we are interested in high availability, we are intrigued by distributed systems, we like to experiment with emerging technologies, we take pride in the applications we write, deploy and maintain. And we are fortunate enough to be able to live our passion through our jobs. Paylogic is a company that is both commercially and technically quite ambitious. Its goal is to redesign the world of ticketing with creative and reliable ticketing solutions which empower the event organizer in their relation with their visitors. The commercial ambitions are achieved through technical leadership. Technical leadership is achieved by both hiring top software engineers and selecting the right technologies and tools. One of the fundamental choices in that respect is the commitment to open source software. Paylogic is fully built upon open source software and firmly rooted in the open source culture. Some key technologies we use are for example Python, SQLAlchemy, Django, Flask, JavaScript and MySQL. Interestingly enough the Zen of Python is largely used as guidance for running the technical side of Paylogic. But we are not just using open source software, we are also actively giving back. We contribute to many open source projects, we run PyGrunn, the biggest Python conference in the Netherlands, we open source as much of the software we write as possible, we give lectures at universities about our work, and we participate in a number of open source related conferences. Somehow all of our open source efforts were quite detached and independent. This developer portal and blog should change that. This will be the central hub for the outside world to learn about the technology within Paylogic. We will announce open source projects and write about technical topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end it is all about sharing, and we share because we care. We hope you appreciate our effort and share back. Whether it is code, ideas or feedback. So welcome to the tech world of Paylogic and please join the discussions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term=""></category></entry></feed>